Register of the Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev papers
1930-1968
2000C86
Hoover Institution Archives
7 microfilm reels (1.0 linear foot
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and printed matter, relating to Russian émigré lawyers in the United States, and to resettlement of Russian refugees in the United States.
Nikolaev, K. N. (Konstantin Nikolaevich), 1884-1965
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2003 and 2008
Location of Originals
In part, Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1884, April 12 Born, Kiev, Russia
1905 Graduated, Iiuridicheskii fakul'tet Imperatorskogo Kievskogo universiteta Sv. Vladimira
1911-1918 Attorney in Kiev, Russia
1920 May Arrived in Warsaw, Poland
1926-1933 Legal advisor to the Orthodox Church in Poland
1927 Author, Sud prisiazhnykh v Rossii (1864-1917) Author, Pravovoe polozhenie Sv. Avtokefal'noi Tserkvi v Pol'she
1931 Author, Vossoedinenie uniatov s Pravoslavnoi Tser-kov'iu v 1839 g.i Konkordat Rima s Rossiei v 1847 g.
1933-1944 Lived in Belgrade, Yugoslavia
1934 Author, Pravovoe polozhenie Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi i naroda russkogo v rasseianii sushchego
1946 Organized the Union of Russian Jurists in Germany
1950 Author, Vostochnyi obriad Organized the Union of Russian Jurists Former DPs in the USA, serves as chair
1965 June 26 Died, New York, NY
Scope and Content Note for the Museum of Russian Culture materials
The papers of a leading émigré activist and lawyer, Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev (1884-1965). It includes Nikolaev's correspondence with other Russian émigrés, and German and American authorities, regarding the resettling of Russian refugees in the United States following the Second World War, as well as materials relating to two émigré legal organizations directed by Nikolaev.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Scope and Content Note for the Holy Trinity Seminary materials
These papers provide insight into the life of the Orthodox Church in Poland in the Interwar period, where Konstantin Nikolaev served as legal advisor to the Orthodox Church in Poland, until he was forced into exile to Yugoslavia, where he continued to be active in the offices of Patriarch Varnava and Metropolitan Anastasii. Nikolaev was a defender of human rights, especially in regards to the Russian émigrés, which is reflected in this collection, particularly in the Subject File in the papers of the Union of Russian Jurists. Therefore, these papers reflect his activities on behalf of Russian émigrés at large.
The Correspondence is mainly of a personal nature, however, the Subject File includes detailed correspondence related to Nikolaev's role as chair of the Union of Russian Jurists Former DPs in the USA, which was founded by him as a continuation of the Union of Russian Jurists in Germany, which he also established.
Nikolaev's legal and advocacy activities are also reflected in his Speeches and Writings, which are in part represented in these papers. Particularly significant in this regard are "Bor'ba russkikh tserkovnykh i obshchestvennykh organizatsii za zhizn' russkikh DP v Germanii," and "Istoriia dieiatel'nosti russkikh tserkovnykh i obshchestvennykh organizatsii v okkupatsionnykh zonakh Germanii po zashchitie zhizni i svobody b. sovietskikh grazhdan pred amerikanskimi vlastiami." Also significant is his memoir, "Moi zhiznennyi put'," which describes his early life, military career, service in the White Army during the Russian Civil War, and émigré activities.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Biography
Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev was born on April 12, 1884, in Kiev, Russia. A graduate of the Law Department of Kiev University of St. Vladimir, Nikolaev worked as an attorney in Kiev until 1918. In 1920 he immigrated to Warsaw, Poland, where he served as legal adviser to the Orthodox Church and held other diocesan assignments. In 1933, Nikolaev was exiled to Belgrade, Serbia, where he continued to advise church hierarchy on legal affairs. In this capacity, he worked closely with Patriarch Varnava (Rusich) of the Serbian Orthodox Church and Metropolitan Anastasii (Gribanovskii) of the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia. Leaving Belgrade in 1944, Nikolaev spent the next two years in Germany involved in defense of human rights, especially concerning Russian refugees. In 1946 he founded the Union of Former Russian Jurists in Germany, reestablishing this organization in the United States after his arrival there in 1950. As chair of this organization, Nikolaev continued his efforts on behalf of the Russian émigré community.
Nikolaev authored several books on jurisprudence and church history, was a contributor to various émigré periodicals, and published and edited the journal Za pravo i pravdu. He died in New York on June 26, 1965.
International relief.; Lawyers--Russia.; Lawyers--United States.; Refugees.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Museum of Russian Culture materials microfilm (Microfilm reels 1-4)
  - Biographical File, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Clipping about Nikolaev
  - Correspondence, 1946-1951
    General note
    See also Subject File/Obshchestvo russkikh zarubezhnykh iuristov
    Arrangement note
    Organized alphabetically by name of correspondent and in subject files of the donor's creation
    - General. (Folder 1: 1)
      Files created by Nikolaev
      - "Perepiska s obshchestvennymi uchrezhdeniiami, uchenymi i redaktsiiami,", 1946-1949 (Folder 1: 2)
      - "Perepiska s raznymi litsami,", 1946-1948 (Folder 1: 3-5)
      - "Perepiska s raznymi litsami,", 1946-1948 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Gol'denveizer, Aleksei Aleksandrovich, 1945-1949 (Folder 2: 2)
      Includes related bulletins, clippings, legal documents, and notices
    - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1951 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1947-1952
    Newspaper columns and one booklet
    - General - Newspaper columns, 1949-1952 (Folder 2: 4-6)
      Includes table of contents for each folder
    - Prorocheskii smysl russkoi literatury, 1947 (Folder 2: 7)
      Printed copy
    - Pathless, 1948 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Subject File, 1946-1960 (Box 3)
    Circulars, clippings, correspondence, certificates, periodicals and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by heading
    - Lawyers, Russian (Folder 3: 1)
    - Ob"edinenie russkikh iuristov b. Di-Pi v Amerike (Folder 3: 2)
    - Obshchestvo russkikh zarubezhnykh iuristov
      - Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Folder 3: 3)
      - Office file. (Folder 3: 4)
        Includes certificates, clippings, circulars and related matter
      - Printed matter. (Folder 3: 5-6)
        Includes published reports, brochures and periodical entitled Zapiski Obschestva russkikh zarubezhnykh iuristov
- Holy Trinity Seminary materials microfilm (Microfilm reels 5-7)
  - Biographical File, 1930-1968 and undated. (Box 1)
    Includes biographical information, curriculum vitae, identification documents, and immigration records. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
    - Clippings, 1947-1961 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1945-1968 and undated. (Folder 1: 2)
      Includes biographical sketches
    - Gramota of the Russian Orthodox Church, correspondence relating to, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Identification documents, 1930 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Immigration records, 1948-1949 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1964 and undated.
    See also Subject File/Union of Russian Jurists Former DPs in the USA file
    Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
    - General, 1956-1957 and undated (Folder 1: 6)
    - Unidentified, 1951-1958 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Agreneva-Slavianskaia, Margarita, 1957 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Aver'ino, Zakharii Pavlovich, 1954 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Avondrood, Igor Konstantinovich, 1956 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Bel'deminov, Sergei I., 1948. (Folder 1: 11)
      Includes "K ubiistvu verkhovnogo pravitelia admiral A. V. Kolchaka," undated. Typescript
    - Bozhenko, Mariia, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Chirkov, N., 1957 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Chugunov, T. K., 1957 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Danilovskii, A., 1958 (Folder 1: 15)
    - de Dieck, Polina Aleksandrovna, 1956 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Dubrovskii, Vsevolod Konstantinovich, 1957 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Glazenap, Petr Vladimirovich, 1949 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Glebov, Ivan A., 1956 (Folder 1: 19)
    - Holy Trinity Monastery, 1950-1960 and undated (Folder 1: 20)
    - Iakovlev, D., 1956 and undated (Folder 1: 21)
    - Kalinovich, Pavel, Reverend, 1954 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Kalishevskii, A. N., 1956 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Khodnev, Dimitrii, 1957 (Folder 1: 24)
    - Kobylin, Viktor Sergeevich, 1956-1958 (Folder 1: 25)
    - Kriabrova, Irina Nikolaevna, 1957 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Latyshev, S. and E., 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 27)
    - Lekhno, Valentin Iosifovich, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 28)
    - Levitskii, Dimitrii Aleksandrovich, 1957 (Folder 1: 29)
    - Lutskaia, Ferida, 1957 (Folder 1: 30)
    - Lyzlov, Evgenii, Reverend, 1952-1957 (Folder 1: 31)
    - Maevskii, Vladislav Al'bionovich, 1956 (Folder 1: 32)
    - Mal'tseva, Antonina Ivanovna, 1957 (Folder 1: 33)
    - Merzheevskii, Vladimir Danilovich, 1957 (Folder 1: 34)
    - Mikhailovskii, A., 1956 (Folder 1: 35)
    - Mirov, Dimitrii Stepanovich, 1956 (Folder 1: 36)
    - Mitkevich, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1957 (Folder 1: 37)
    - Nashe vremia, 1953 (Folder 1: 38)
    - Naumov, A., 1956 (Folder 1: 39)
    - Pol'skii, Mikhail, Reverend, 1956 (Folder 1: 40)
    - Popov, P. A., 1957 (Folder 1: 41)
    - Pronin, Feodor Maksimovich, 1957 (Folder 1: 42)
    - Pronin, Vasilii Mikhailovich, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 43)
    - Proshin, K., 1957 (Folder 1: 44)
    - Prozar, N., 1956 (Folder 1: 45)
    - Russian Corps Combattants (Soiuz chinov Russkogo Korpusa), undated (Folder 1: 46)
    - Sadovskaia, T., undated (Folder 1: 47)
    - Samoilenko, Feodor Petrovich, 1954. (Folder 1: 48)
      Includes holograph of short memoir
    - Savva (Raevskii), Archbishop, 1957-1964 (Folder 1: 49)
    - Semchevskii, Konstantin Vasil'evich, 1956 (Folder 1: 50)
    - Shapovalova, Nataliia, 1954 (Folder 1: 51)
    - Slavinskaia, M., 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 52)
    - Soglasie, 1953 (Folder 1: 53)
    - Speranskaia, M., 1957 and undated (Folder 1: 54)
    - Stefan (Sevbo), Archbishop, 1960 (Folder 1: 55)
    - Stuart, G., 1957 (Folder 1: 56)
    - Sukalo, A., 1954. (Folder 1: 57)
      Includes typescript of short memoir
    - Svitich, Aleksandr, 1957 (Folder 1: 58)
    - Terent'ev, Leonid Petrovich, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 59)
    - Timofeev, Mr., 1957 (Folder 1: 60)
    - Timoshenko, Elena Petrovna, 1956 (Folder 1: 61)
    - Vasil'ev, Sergei Aleksandrovich, 1954-1956 (Folder 1: 62)
    - Vinogradov, A., 1957 (Folder 1: 63)
    - Voskoboinikov, Aleksandr, 1956-1957 and undated (Folder 1: 64)
    - Zhar-Ptitsa, 1956 (Folder 1: 65)
    - Zlatostviet, 1957 (Folder 1: 66)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1934-1963. (Box 2)
    Articles, clippings, drafts, pamphlets, and speeches, arranged chronologically by title
    - General - Reviews, 1934-1954 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Untitled, undated. (Folder 2: 2)
      Typescripts
    - "K istorii bor'by za zhizn' i svobodu russkikh liudei v Evrope, poslie kapituliatsii Germanii,", undated. (Folder 2: 3)
      Holograph
    - "Pravo i sud,", undated. (Folder 2: 4)
      Holograph. Includes related correspondence
    - Prorocheskii smysl russkoi literatury deviatnadtsatago vieka, 1947. (Folder 2: 5)
      Typescript
    - "Rech' K. N. Nikolaeva na torzhestvennom sobranii v chest' arkhiereiskago sobora Russkoi Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi zagranitsei 10 dekabria 1950 goda v gorodie N'iu-Iorkie," (Folder 2: 6)
    - "Bor'ba russkikh tserkovnykh i obshchestvennykh organizatsii za zhizn' russkikh DP v Germanii,", 1951. (Folder 2: 7)
    - "Den' russkoi skorbi,", 1951. (Folder 2: 8)
      Printed copy. Includes dedication on cover by author, signed October 4, 1951
    - "Lev Nikolaevich Tolstoi. Smysl ego izobrazitel'nogo tvorchestva." (Folder 2: 9)
      Includes associated correspondence, 1953-1954
    - "Russkii sud," typescript. (Folder 2: 10)
      Includes related correspondence, 1953
    - Vatikan, Kiev, Moskva,", 1953. (Folder 2: 11)
    - "Vostochnyi obriad i ego vozrozhdenie v Sievernoi i Iuzhnoi Amerikie v sviazi s razvitiem uniatstva v Kanadie"
      - Typescript, 1953 (Folder 2: 12)
      - Reviews, 1954 and undated (Folder 2: 13)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Folder 2: 14)
    - "Apostol'skaia administratsiia na Lemkovshchine,", 1954. (Folder 2: 15)
    - "Bor'ba za tserkovnoe dostoianie Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi v Pol'she,", 1954. (Folder 2: 16)
    - "Iz dalekoi solnechnoi Kalifornii,", 1954. (Folder 2: 17)
    - "Istoriia dieiatel'nosti russkikh tserkovnykh i obshchestvennykh organizatsii v okkupatsionnykh zonakh Germanii po zashchitie zhizni i svobody b. sovietskikh grazhdan pred amerikanskimi vlastiami,", undated. (Folder 2: 18)
      Typescript, incomplete. Includes related correspondence
    - "Moi zhiznennyi put',", 1958. (Folder 2: 19-22)
      Typescript, includes handwritten corrections
    - "Antonii Khrapovitskii, Metropolitan," notes and review, 1963. (Folder 2: 23)
      Holograph, printed copy, typescript
  - Writings by Others, 1946-1947 and undated. (Box 3)
    Arranged alphabetically by author
    - Unidentified
      - "Postanovka iuridicheskogo obrazovaniia v Sovetskoi Rossii,", 1947. (Folder 3: 1)
      - "Ukrainskaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov',", 1946. (Folder 3: 2)
    - Salatko, B. N.
      - "Zapiski sovietskago advokata,", undated. (Folder 3: 3)
  - Subject File, 1946-1962.
    Brochures, clippings, correspondence, minutes of meetings, notes, and official documents leaflets, organizational documents, and pamphlets, arranged alphabetically by subject
    - Catholicism, 1955-1961 and undated (Folder 3: 4)
    - Displaced persons
      - General, 1947-1948 and undated. (Folder 3: 5)
        Includes clippings
      - Amnesty, 1954 and undated (Folder 3: 6)
    - Dom Russkoi Kul'tury, undated (Folder 3: 7)
    - House of Free Russia, 1950-1955 and undated (Folder 3: 8)
    - Medvietskii, S., 1954 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Union of Russian Jurists Former DPs in the USA
      - General
        - General, 1946 and undated (Folder 3: 10)
        - Correspondence
          - 1948-1951 and undated (Folder 3: 11)
          - 1952 (Folder 3: 12)
          - 1953-1954 (Folder 3: 13)
        - Minutes of meetings, 1947-1956. (Folder 3: 14)
          Includes resolutions
      - American Civil Liberty Union, undated (Folder 3: 15)
      - Displaced Persons Commission
        - General, 1950 (Folder 3: 16)
        - Case files
          - Langer, Alexandr, 1950-1952 (Folder 3: 17)
          - Pushkarskii, Nikolai Iiulianovich, 1950-1951 (Folder 3: 18)
      - Russian Orthodox Church, 1954-1962 and undated (Folder 3: 19)
      - United States Senate, 1954 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Photograph, undated
    - One print of Konstantin N. Nikolaev at a banquet with a group of unidentified people, undated (Folder 3: 21)